[Music]
though we often hear new cancer drugs
described as game-changing breakthroughs
most of four much more modest benefits
in my last video i quoted a recent
editorial in the journal of the national
cancer institute suggesting that the
majority of new cancer drugs don't
deliver clinically meaningful benefits
at all
at least when they're later proven to be
ineffective they're pulled from the
market right
no even when post-market studies show
the new drugs to have no clinical
meaningful benefit compared to not just
older drugs but compared to nothing
compared to a sugar pill most chemo
drugs retain fda approval and remain on
the market even at the same
ridiculous prices in fact the most
expensive drug they looked at the one
costing 169 836 dollars a year did not
improve overall survival at all and
actually worsened quality of life 169
thousand dollars just to make you feel
worse
with no benefit why pay a penny for
treatment that doesn't actually help and
even when they do improve survival what
does that actually mean
currently the trend is for big pharma to
design large trials that may detect
statistically significant but often
trivial differences in survival
endpoints for example check out this
famous trial adding this second drug or
lotinib to gemcitibean for advanced
pancreatic cancer significantly
prolonged overall survival
yeah they suffered more side effects but
we're not just talking about tumor
shrinkage they lived significantly
longer
the placebo group only lived 5.91 months
whereas the added drug group survived
all the way to
6.24 months
wait a second
they only lived a third of a month
longer
that's just 10 days right all the side
effects and expense for an average of
just
10 days
that's why doctors shouldn't use this
statistical jargon significant
improvement in survival while informing
patients about benefits of new treatment
when patients hear the word survival
they're not thinking about a week and a
half
if you put all the new chemo drugs
together approved over the last dozen
years the average overall survival
benefit is
2.1 months now look
two months is two months i don't want to
downplay that but you know time and
again surveys have indicated that
patients expect much more
incredibly about three quarters of
patients with metastatic lung or
colorectal cancer did not report
understanding that their chemo was not
at all likely to cure their cancer i
mean that's the primary treatment but
the chemo's not curative it's just
eeking out a few extra weeks or months
why weren't the majority of patients
told that
it's not that they were being over
optimistic explaining the researcher
they were under the mistaken belief that
the treatment offered a chance of cure
when it in fact didn't
that deprives patients of the
opportunity to you know weigh the risks
and benefits and make their own
decisions about their own body
if you ask cancer patients
most want at least a half a year to
stomach the side effects which suggests
that most cancer patients might not
choose chemotherapy if they knew how
little they'd actually benefit but look
everyone's different you know one
patient they interviewed said living
even one week longer would be worth it
whereas another said they wouldn't even
want to do chemo for two extra years of
life they wouldn't want anything to
interfere with the quality of the time
they had left
either way people deserve to know the
truth i find it telling that oncologists
and cancer nurses themselves express
less willingness to accept intensive
chemotherapy given the associated
toxicities
most chemo drugs are cytotoxic meaning
they work by killing off cancer cells
but they also kill off some healthy
cells as collateral damage which is you
know
why they can damage our nerves cause you
know irreversible heart failure slough
off the linings of our gut or damage
your immune system
drug companies frequently downplay the
risks though for example
describing this breast cancer drug as
having acceptable side effect profiles
for most patients or or this pancreatic
cancer drug is having a manageable and
mostly reversible safety profile
these were studies published in top
medical journals right
naturally readers would take these
statements to be true however if you
actually look at the data the number of
serious even life-threatening side
effects was double or even five times
higher on the new breast cancer drug and
the manageable and mostly reversible
side effects evidently weren't referring
to those who were killed by the drug
i like how they even included like a
cheat sheet acceptable toxicity
acceptable to whom right manageable
serious events and deaths can never be
considered manageable and feasible
who would sign up for a drug whose
toxicity could only be described as
feasible
favorable
compared to what tolerable
that's for the patient to decide and any
drug that kills people can hardly be
considered safe
still
patients may very well consider it worth
the risk
for some cancers we've made tremendous
strides right testicular cancer for
example there's greater than a one in
three chance that chemotherapy could
enable you to survive at least to the
five year mark same with hodgkin's
disease a relatively rare form of
lymphoma but even when researchers try
to err on the side of overestimating the
benefit for most common cancers colon
lung breast and prostate the chances
appear to be more like one or two
percent
[Music]
you